Guide to the Low, Fleming, and King Family Papers 1794-1945 MS 3091
New-York Historical Society
Low, Fleming, and King family papers
1794-1945
New-York Historical Society
MS 3091
0.42 Linear feet in 1 document box and 1 oversize folder.
Correspondence, documents, and ephemera stemming from the related Low, Fleming, and King families. Includes a 1794 letter to New York merchant and developer Nicholas Low (1739-1826) from Alexander Hamilton, and letters to the firm Low & Wallace from American and European importers and exporters, such as the Widow John Lang, Son & Co. of Bremen. Also present are a number of 19th century United States revenue stamps that were torn or soaked from documents by a collector.
Access Restrictions
This collection may be stored offsite. To arrange to consult it, please go to www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection, the gift of Noëlle King and the King family, was received in two parts: the bulk in 2018 (accession no. MS.2018.049), and the oversized commission in Series III in 2019 (accession no. MS-2019-001).
Arrangement
The collection is organized in five series, with material sorted chronologically within each series:
Series I
Nicholas Low and Low & Wallace, 1794-1814
Series II
Augustus Fleming, 1828-1865
Series III
King family, 1861-1934
Series IV
Miscellaneous documents, 1868-1908, undated
Series V
Philately, postal history, numismatics, circa 1862-1945, undated
Biographical / Historical
Late in life, New York merchant and developer Nicholas Low (1739-1826) married Alice (Haliburton) Fleming, a widow who brought two sons to the marriage, one of whom was Augustus Fleming (1785-1865). Low's children with Alice included a daughter, Henrietta Liston Low (1799-1882), who married (as his second wife) Charles King (1789-1867), son of diplomat Rufus King (1755-1827). Among the children of Charles and Henrietta (Low) King was Cornelius Low King (1829–1893). By his first marriage Charles King had a son, Rufus King (1814-1876), who, in turn, had a son named Rufus King Jr. (1838-1900). (All names underlined are represented by documents in the present collection.)
Related Archival Materials
The New-York Historical Society also holds the Nicholas Low Papers (1 box), the Nicholas Low Papers supplement (167 items), and a further cache of Nicholas Low papers supplementary to the Elizabeth M. Smith Collection (30 items).
Scope and Contents
Merchant Nicholas Low (1739–1826), in partnership with his brothers-in-law Hugh and Alexander Wallace, and nephew, William Wallace, imported Irish linens, salt, gunpowder, dry goods, and wine, while exporting corn, wheat, tobacco, rice, cotton, potash, and flaxseed. The collection includes letters from a number of his business contacts such as Magrath & Higgins (Madeira), Post & Russell (New York), Widow John Lang, Son & Co. (Bremen), James Waring & Co. (London), Richard H. Wilcocks & Co. (Philadelphia), and Ramsey, Gatchell and Bancroft (Waterford, Ireland). Also present is a 1794 letter from Alexander Hamilton, the postscript to which congratulates Low on his recent marriage, and a letter from Low's daughter, Henrietta, showing concern for the fate of Baltimore in the days following the British attack on Fort McHenry of September 13–14, 1814. (See Series I.)
Augustus Fleming, stepson of Nicholas Low, is represented by a few items: one letter (1828), a receipt (1865), and canceled checks (1845, 1863–1864). (See Series II.)
Nicholas Low's daughter, Henrietta Liston Low (1799-1882), married Charles King (1789-1867), son of diplomat Rufus King (1755-1827), so the collection includes some material (largely correspondence and receipts) from their descendants, such as the commission of son Cornelius Low King (1829–1893) as First Lieutenant in the 14th Regiment of Infantry during the Civil War. (See Series III.)
A group of miscellaneous documents—some possibly originating with the King family, but not identified as such—includes letters, receipts, two printed items to the Veterans of the Seventh Regiment, and a photoreproduction of a bas relief portrait of Abraham Lincoln. (See Series IV).
The collection includes an assemblage probably made by a numismatist and/or a philatelist, as it contains examples of foreign paper currency, and postage and revenue stamps torn or soaked from documents (in many cases the stamps remain attached to fragments of documents). In August 1862, the United States (Union) government began taxing various goods, services, and legal transactions. Taxes were paid by purchasing a revenue stamp of the appropriate denomination and affixing it to the taxable item. (See Series V.)
Business letters.; Checks (bank checks); Covers (closures); Personal correspondence; Paper money.; Postage stamps; Receipts (financial records); Tax stamps; Numismatics; Shipping -- New York (State) -- New York.; Stamp collecting; Fleming, Augustus, 1785-1865; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804; King, Cornelius Low, 1829-1893; King, Henrietta Liston (Low), 1799–1882; King, Rufus, 1814-1876; King, Rufus, Jr., 1838-1900; Low, Nicholas, 1739-1826; Wilcocks, Richard H. (Richard Hockley), 1776-; Low & Wallace (New York, N.Y.); Society for Establishing Useful Manufactures; Widow John Lang, Son & Co. (Bremen)
- Series I. Nicholas Low and Low & Wallace, 1794-1814
  - Letter from Alexander Hamilton (Philadelphia) to Nicholas Low (New York), 1794 September 17 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Transcription:
    General Schuyler directed [t]hat when the time came for paying for a coach building for him here, I should draw upon you for the money. That time is come & I am not otherwise provided so that I have this day drawn upon you in favour of John Kean Esq for the cost being Fifteen hundred Dollars what I request you to pay & charge to him. We are all alive here preparing for the [Insurgents?] Yours A Hamilton
    P.S. Is it true that I ought to congratulate you on having become a benedict [i.e., a newly married man]. If so accept my heartfelt congratulations [illegible] N Low Esq
  - Letters (2) from Peter Colt (Paterson, N.J.) to Nicholas Low (New York), 1795 May 14, 24 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Nicholas Low was a director of the Society for Establishing Useful Manufactures in Paterson, New Jersey, and became its governor in 1792. The Society sought to make Paterson a center of cotton manufacturing, but the venture was ultimately unsuccessful, and the Society folded in 1796.
  - Letter from Magrath & Higgins (Madeira) to Low & Wallace (New York), 1804 June 23 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Original + manuscript copy.
  - Letter from Post & Russell (New York) to Low & Wallace (New York), 1804 October 25 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Post & Russell were agents for the ship Ophelia.
  - Letters (6) from Widow John Lang, Son & Co. (Bremen) to Low & Wallace (New York), 1805-1806 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Dated 1805 August 5; 1806 March 4, May 2, May 8, May 16, August 2.
  - Letter from James Waring & Co. (London) to Low & Wallace (New York) [copy], 1806 April 29 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Indenture, William Wallace and John Shaw, bound to the United States of America, $300.00., 1806 November 10 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters (2) from Richard H. Wilcocks & Co. (Philadelphia) to Low & Wallace (New York), 1806 September 6, November 15 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letter from Ramsey, Gatchell and Bancroft (Waterford, Ireland) to Low & Wallace (New York), 1807 October 7 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letter from Henrietta Low (Claverack, N.Y.) to her father, Nicholas Low (Ballston Springs, N.Y.), 1814 September 17 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Henrietta Low, writing to her father just a few days after the British attack on Fort McHenry of September 13-14, 1814, mentions how "We are all here anxious about the fate of Baltimore but the southern mail had not come in when the latest that we have had was sent to press."
- Series II. Augustus Fleming, 1828-1865
  - Letter from James [_____] (Claverack, N.Y.) to Augustus Fleming (New York), 1828 October 6 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Canceled checks, Bank of New York, 1845 June – November (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Canceled checks, Bank of New York, 1863 September – 1864 July (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Receipt for goods purchased of James G. King's Sons, New York, 1865 June 22 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series III. King family, 1861-1934
  - Covers (4) addressed to Rufus King, 1860s–1880s (Box 1, Folder 15)
    It is unclear if these covers were sent to Rufus King (1814-1876) or to his son, Rufus King Jr. (1838–1900).
  - Commission of Cornelius Low King as First Lieutenant in the 14th Regiment of Infantry., 1861 August 17 (Oversize small)
    Signed by U.S. President Abraham Lincoln and Secretary of War Simon Cameron.
  - Letter from Union League Club to William G. King, 1863 April (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Printed circular letter regarding the Union League Club's upcoming membership drive.
  - King family receipts, 1865–1868 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Weekly Detroit Free Press, vol. 58, no. 19, 1883 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Newspaper with printed subscription label for "Wm. G King."
  - Postal card addressed to "Office of the Low Estate", 1886 February [4] (Box 1, Folder 19)
    The address, "1 Cottage Place, New York City, N.Y.," corresponds to that of Rufus King Jr.
  - Letter from Pavonia Yacht Club (Jersey City) to Rufus King [Jr.] (New York), 1890 September 1 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Combined invitation to board meeting and membership dues receipt, with folding membership card / dues payment register, sent to Rufus King [Jr.], 1 Cottage Place, New York City.
  - Letter from Hughes' Yacht Agency (New York) to Rufus King [Jr.], 1892 November 1 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Covers (6) addressed to Mrs. Charles King, Mrs. Margaret S. King, Mrs. Williams King, 1928–1934 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Series IV. Miscellaneous documents, 1868-1908, undated
  - W. S. Carr receipts (3), 1868 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous receipts (2), 1868 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Printed circular "To the Veterans of the Seventh Regiment," New York, 1889 January 28 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Veterans of the Seventh Regiment, New York, General Orders No. 2, 1889 March 19 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Letter from Hatch & Foote, Bankers (New York) to F. N. Phinney (New York), 1893 January [10] (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Letter and prospectus from Hatch & Foote, mortgage agents, soliciting bond investments in the rolling stock of the Columbus, Shawnee and Hocking Railway Company.
  - Postal cards, 1895, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Addressed to S. O. R. Townsend, New York (1895) and to Miss Dorothy Ely, Philadelphia (1906).
  - Letter from Herbert S. Ogden (New York) to William Ruscoe (Wilton, Conn.), 1906 May 4 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    A list of instructions from Ogden to Ruscoe, who was, apparently, Ogden's gardener and stableman.
  - Abraham Lincoln portrait, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Photoreproduction of Byron M. Pickett's 1873 oval bronze bas relief of Abraham Lincoln's right profile, copyright 1908 by L. G. Muller.
  - Check fragments (2), undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Series V. Philately, postal history, numismatics, circa 1862-1945, undated
  - United States postage stamps, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Foreign postage stamps, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Covers (28) addressed to Miss Charlotte E. Williams (Ithaca, N.Y.), 1903–1916 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Covers (4) addressed to Mrs. J. B. Williams (Ithaca, N.Y.), 1905–1906 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - United States revenue stamps. $0.02 (4 folders), [1862-1872] (Box 1, Folder 36-39)
    Stamps issued for "bank check" and general use.
  - United States revenue stamps. $0.05, [1862-1872] (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Stamps issued for "certificate" and "inland exchange."
  - United States revenue stamps. $0.10, [1862-1872] (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Stamps issued for "contract" and "power of attorney."
  - United States revenue stamps. $0.25, [1862-1872] (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Stamps issued for "insurance" and general use.
  - United States revenue stamps. $0.50, [1862-1872] (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Stamps issued for "foreign exchange," "life insurance," "mortgage," "original process," "surety bond."
  - United States revenue stamps. $1.00, [1862-1872] (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Stamps issued for "inland exchange."
  - United States revenue stamps. $1.50, [1862-1872] (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Stamps issued for "general use."
  - United States revenue stamps. $2.00, [1862-1872] (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Stamps issued for "conveyance," "mortgage," "probate of will."
  - United States revenue stamps. $3.00, [1862-1872] (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Stamps issued for "charter party."
  - United States revenue stamps. Multiple denominations, [1862-1872] (Box 1, Folder 48)
    $0.05. "Certificate," "inland exchange," general use.
    $0.10. "Contract."
    $0.25. "Certificate," "entry of goods."
    $0.50. "Conveyance," "foreign exchange," "original process."
    $1.00. "Manifest."
    $2.00. "Conveyance," "mortgage."
  - Foreign currency, 1941–1945 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    100 Yuan, China (1941)
    1,000 pesos, Japanese Government, Philippines (1945)
    5 Yen, Japan (undated)